# Paris Koloveas

# Data Science Researcher, NLP Researcher, ML Engineer, Data Engineer

Email: pkoloveas@uop.gr Google Scholar: users.uop.gr/pkoloveas GitHub: github.com/pkoloveas

Phone: TBF LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/pkoloveas Residence: Athens, GR

Research interests Natural Language Processing, Large Language Models, Deep Learning, Machine Learning,

Data Mining, Text Classification, Scientometrics and Bibliometrics, Information Retrieval,

Information Extraction, Data Visualisation

Summary

I am a Data Science Researcher, mainly focused on Natural Language Processing & Understanding tasks. As a PhD candidate in Scientometrics, my research focuses on the analysis of scientific publications using NLP and Deep Learning techniques. I am particularly interested in Citation Intent Classification, which involves identifying the purpose of citations in publications to provide insights into their impact. Previously, my focus has been around

applications of NLP in the Cyber-Security domain, specifically, text mining, information

filtering and knowledge extraction for Cyber-Threat Intelligence discovery.

Education University of the Peloponnese

Apr 2021 – Present

PhD in Computer Science

Supervisor: Prof. C. Tryfonopoulos

Thesis: Context-aware information extraction for scientific impact prediction in scholarly

publications.

NCSR Demokritos & University of the Peloponnese

Oct 2019 - Feb 2021

MSc in Data Science

GPA: 9.29/10

Supervisor: Prof. C. Tryfonopoulos

Thesis: A machine learning framework for gathering and leveraging web data to Cyber-

Threat Intelligence.

University of the Peloponnese

Oct 2014 – Sep 2019

BSc in Informatics & Telecommunications

GPA: 7.32/10

Supervisor: Prof. C. Tryfonopoulos

Thesis: Web content harvesting and classification for Cyber-Threat Intelligence discovery.

Work experience

Information Management Systems Institute (IMSI), Dept. of Big Data Research Infrastructures, Athens, GR Jan 2023 – Present

**Athena Research & Innovation Centre** 

Role: Research Associate, Developer

Supervisor: Dr. T. Vergoulis

Responsibilities:

- 1. Participation in Research Projects (**GraspOS**, **SciLake**) with the main goal of the research, development, documentation and deployment of software solutions, as well as, the authorship of technical reports and research papers.
- 2. Enhancement and maintenance of the BIP! Services platform.
- 3. Development of operations and workflows for the enrichment of the OpenAIRE Graph
- 4. Setup, maintenance and operationalization of AWS instances for research experiments.

Software and Database Systems Laboratory (SoDa Lab), Dept. of Informatics & Telecommunications,

Mar 2018 – Present

Tripolis, GR

University of the Peloponnese

Role: Research Assistant, Research Software Engineer

Supervisor: Prof. C. Tryfonopoulos

Responsibilities:

- 1. Participation in Research Projects (**Cyber-Trust**, **FORESIGHT**, **ENIRISST+**) with the main goal of the research, development, documentation and deployment of software solutions, as well as, the authorship of technical reports and research papers.
- Sub-reviewer in conference and journal submissions at: ICTAI '19-'24, CIKM '20-'24, AIST '21, TPDL '22, SciK '22, '24, KAIS '22-'23, Nature SciRep '21, MDPI ApplSci '21, DSAA '23, SIGIR '23-'24
- 3. Teaching Assistant for the following undergraduate courses:

  Programming II, Data Structures, Information Retrieval and Mining, Big Data
  Management

Mathema SRL Florence, IT

Role: Software Development Intern

Jul 2019 - Oct 2019

*Responsibilities*: Research and development of VR "Control Room" for real-time Information Visualization and Interaction with Unity3D & Oculus SDK.

Research projects

SciLake: Democratising and making sense out of heterogenous Jan 2023 – Present scholarly content.

Affiliation: Athena RC

Funding: HORIZON EUROPE [link]

**GraspOS: next Generation Research Assessment to Promote**Jan 2023 – Present Open Science.

Affiliation: Athena RC

Funding: HORIZON EUROPE [link]

ENIRISST+: Extension of Intelligent Research Infrastructure for Shipping, Supply chain, Transport and Logistics.

May 2021 – May 2023

Affiliation: University of the Peloponnese

Funding: NSRF - Operational Programme Competitiveness, Entrepreneurship and Innovation (GR) [link]

FORESIGHT: Advanced cyber-security simulation platform for preparedness training in Aviation, Power-grid and Naval environments. Oct 2019 – May 2021

Affiliation: University of the Peloponnese

Funding: Horizon 2020 (EU) [link]

CYBER-TRUST: Advanced Cyber-Threat Intelligence, Detection, and Mitigation Platform for a Trusted Internet of Things.

Jul 2018 – Sep 2021

Affiliation: University of the Peloponnese Funding: Horizon 2020 (EU) [link]

Certifications and Seminars

2nd European Summer School on Artificial Intelligence - 21st Advanced Course on Artificial Intelligence (ESSAI - ACAI 2024)

By ESSAI - ACAI Organising Committee

**Natural Language Processing Specialization** 

2021

By DeepLearning.AI - Coursera

**Publications** 

S. Chatzopoulos, <u>P. Koloveas</u>, K. Vichos, T. Vergoulis, **Easing the burden of creating and managing narrative CVs in academia (Poster)**, In the World Conference on Research Integrity (WCRI), Athens, Greece, June 2024.

P. Koloveas, S. Chatzopoulos, C. Tryfonopoulos, and T. Vergoulis, BIP! NDR (NoDoiRefs): A Dataset of Citations from Papers Without DOIs in Computer Science Conferences and Workshops, In the 27th International Conference on Theory and Practice of Digital Libraries (TPDL), Zadar, Croatia, September 2023.

G. Fotopoulos, <u>P. Koloveas</u>, P. Raftopoulou, and C. Tryfonopoulos, **Comparing Data Store Performance for Full-Text Search: to SQL or to NoSQL?**, *In the 12th International Conference on Data Science, Technology and Applications (DATA), Rome, Italy, July 2023.* 

<u>P. Koloveas</u>, T. Chantzios, C. Tryfonopoulos, and S. Skiadopoulos, **Cyber-Threat Intelligence** (Book Chapter), Security Technologies and Methods for Advanced Cyber Threat Intelligence, Detection and Mitigation, Now Publishers, 2022.

P. Koloveas, T. Chantzios, S. Alevizopoulou, C. Tryfonopoulos, and S. Skiadopoulos, in-TIME: A Machine Learning-Based Framework for Gathering and Leveraging Web Data to Cyber-Threat Intelligence, In: MDPI Electronics, Special issue on "Advances on Networks and Cyber Security", March 2021.

S. Alevizopoulou, <u>P. Koloveas</u>, C. Tryfonopoulos, P. Raftopoulou, **Social Media Monitoring for IoT Cyber-Threats**, *In the Workshop on Data Science for Cyber Security (DS4CS @ IEEE CSR)*, *Rhodes*, *Greece*, *July 2021*.

P. Koloveas, T. Chantzios, C. Tryfonopoulos, and S. Skiadopoulos, A crawler for harvesting the clear, social, and dark web for IoT-related Cyber-Threat Intelligence, In the IEEE Workshop on Cyber Security & Resilience in the Internet of Things (CSRIoT@IEEE Services), Milan, Italy, July 2019.

T. Chantzios, <u>P. Koloveas</u>, S. Skiadopoulos, N. Kolokotronis, C. Tryfonopoulos, V. Bilali, and D. Kavallieros, **The quest for the appropriate Cyber-Threat Intelligence sharing platform**, *In the 8th International Conference on Data Science, Technology and Applications (DATA), Prague, Czech Republic, July 2019.* 

Awards and Scholarships

### Erasmus+ Scholarship

2019

University of the Peloponnese

Technical skills

## **PROGRAMMING**

Proficient in: Python, Java, C, UNIX Shell Scripting, PHP Familiar with: R, C#, JavaScript (ES6, ReactJS), MATLAB

#### **DATA MANAGEMENT TECHNOLOGIES**

MongoDB, ElasticSearch, Hadoop/HDFS, Neo4j, PostgreSQL, MySQL

#### **OTHER**

Docker, AWS, DigitalOcean, Git, SVN, LaTeX, Notion, Microsoft Office

Languages

Greek - Native Speaker

English - Full Professional Proficiency (CEFR level C2)

Michigan Certificate of Proficiency in English

**French** – Elementary Proficiency (CEFR level B2) Diplôme d'Etudes en Langue Française DELF B2